Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.13
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Dick Thornburgh Papers, Series XIII. Attorney General of the United States
1988-1991
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Thornburgh, Dick
AIS.1998.30.13
228.75 Linear Feet
On July 12, 1988, President Reagan formally requested that Dick Thornburgh serve as his Attorney General, following the resignation of Edwin Meese, with only five months remaining in his presidency. On November 19, then President-elect Bush asked Thornburgh to stay on. Three years later, on April 4, 1991, the news of Pennsylvania Senator John Heinz's tragic death in a plane crash ultimately resulted in Thornburgh's resignation in August 1991 to run for the U.S. Senate. During his tenure, Thornburgh's priorities concentrated on drug trafficking, organized and white-collar crime, civil rights, antitrust and environmental fields. Major topics include: savings and loans scandals, Bank of Credit and Commerce International (BCCI) money laundering scandal, and Banca Nazionale del Lavoro (BNL). Thornburgh signed the United Nations Drug Convention in Vienna, December 1989, and participated in major TREVI (Terrorism, Radicalism, Extremism, Violence International) meetings. The war on drugs extended to South and Central America and topics include the apprehension of Noriega. Other topics are, for example: Project Triggerlock (regarding violent career criminals), the terrorist bombing of Pan Am flight 103, the bombing and death of Judge Robert Vance, Operation Weed and Seed, Superfund hazardous waste cleanup actions, and the Exxon Valdez case. During glasnost Soviet Justice Minister Veniamin F. Yakovlev invited Thornburgh to visit Moscow to discuss democracy, the rule of law, and human rights, the first visit ever by a sitting Attorney General of the United States to the Soviet Union. Thornburgh served as the Bush administration's "point man" for efforts to enact the landmark Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA), signed into law on July 26, 1990. Other matters on the domestic front include Thornburgh's participation in the Council on Competitiveness (CC), the Domestic Policy Council (DPC), Economic Policy Council (EPC), judicial appointment issues, and the so-called Thornburgh Memorandum. The Attorney General files are in fourteen sections: Speeches; News Releases; Transcripts; Nomination and Confirmation; Attorney General's Files; Daily Schedules; Events; Foreign Trips; DPC, EPC, and CC; Department of Justice Issues; Weekly Reports; Correspondence; News Clippings; and Reports. Digital reproductions of portions of the collection are available online.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dick Thornburgh, February 27, 1998.
Previous Citation
Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932-, AIS.1998.30, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Soviet Union; Judges -- Selection and appointment -- United States; Criminal justice, Administration of; Rule of law; Political corruption -- United States; Money laundering; Drug traffic; Drug control; White collar crimes -- United States; Organized crime -- United States; Politics; Government; Personal papers; Thornburgh, Dick; Thornburgh, Ginny (Judson); Yakovlev, Veniamin; Noriega, Manuel Antonio; Kirkpatrick & Lockhart; United States. Attorney-General; United States. Independent Counsel Reauthorization Act of 1987; United States. Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990; World Committee on Disability; Council on Competitiveness (U.S.); Domestic Policy Council (U.S.); Banca nazionale del lavoro; TREVI Group; American Bar Association; National Organization on Disability (U.S.); Office of International Affairs (U.S.); Bank of Credit and Commerce International
- Attorney General of the United States, 1988-1991; XIII.
  Scope and Contents note
  On July 9, 1988, Thornburgh, then Director of Institute of Politics at Harvard University, received a call from the Reagan White House. Edwin Meese, Attorney General of the U.S., had resigned. Thornburgh states in his book: "My law enforcement, political and management record, as well as my good relations with the president and vice president, did seem to make me one of the logical candidates [for Attorney General], but I was hardly expecting Culvahouse's call" (Evidence, p. 201). After several meetings in Washington, with members of the President's staff, Thornburgh met with President Reagan on July 12, who formally requested that Thornburgh serve as his attorney general. This announcement was accompanied generally by very favorable commentary such as that in the New York Times: "Mr. Thornburgh, who made his reputation fighting public corruption, brings an ethical dimension that has rarely been in greater demand." At that time, President Reagan had but five months remaining in his presidency, however, after the election, on November 19, President-elect Bush wasted no time in asking Thornburgh to stay on.
  On October 7, 1988, Thornburgh first addressed the entire department staff, to spell out his priorities which he described as: "a vigorous assault on drug trafficking, a continued focus on organized and white-collar crime and stepped-up activity in the civil rights, antitrust and environmental fields" (see online video). The savings and loan scandal was about to break and was the most pressing challenge in the area of white-collar crime, or what Thornburgh frequently described as "crime in the suites." Ultimately DOJ task forces obtained nearly six hundred convictions, a ninety-three percent conviction rate, over the three years Thornburgh served, with seventy-seven percent of those convicted receiving jail terms.
  Other major white-collar scandals and topics which attracted a lot of attention include: Bank of Credit and Commerce International (BCCI) money laundering scandal, Banca Nazionale del Lavoro (BNL), the Institute for Law and Social Research (INSLAW) case, Iran-Contra (involving issues concerning the independent counsel statute), and the inquiry into Operation Ill Wind.
  In tackling the drug problem, Thornburgh frequently startled his listeners by stating: "If you want to lose the war on drugs, just leave it to law enforcement." As many of his speeches continue: the war against drugs "will not be won in the courtroom ... but in the classroom ... in our churches, homes and communities ... on the field of values." The "Report to the President" on drug trafficking, dated August 3, 1989, is available here online and presents a complete and accurate picture of drug trafficking within the United States and a "roadmap" for enforcement.
  Many of Thornburgh's antidrug activities also involved a stepped-up international offensive. Thornburgh traveled to Vienna to sign the United Nations Drug Convention on behalf of the United States, in December 1989, and attended a number of TREVI (Terrorism, Radicalism, Extremism, Violence International) meetings, which are the law enforcement counterpart to the European Economic Community. The war on drugs also extended to South and Central America and the efforts of Thornburgh and DOJ are well represented in these files, as well as the apprehension of Noriega. "The drug war is an unappetizing battle, first, last and always ... Nevertheless our drug enforcement effort was generally well received, especially in its international aspects" (Evidence, p. 238).
  AG Thornburgh argued two cases before the Supreme Court, the second of which, Payne v. Tennessee, concerned victim's rights, a subject of long standing concern. Other topics well presented in these files are, for example: Project Triggerlock (regarding violent career criminals), the terrorist bombing of Pan Am flight 103, the bombing and death of Judge Robert Vance, Operation Weed and Seed, and Superfund hazardous waste cleanup actions. The Exxon Valdez case resulted in a guilty plea, and fines and restitution which were "by far the largest amount ever paid as a result of environmental violations" (Evidence, p. 250).
  While Thornburgh was Attorney General there generally was a huge increase in activity in the international arena, which in late 1990 resulted in the establishment of a new DOJ Office of International Affairs, at Thornburgh's urging. In September 1990, Thornburgh traveled to Seoul, South Korea, for the first-ever gathering of twenty-four Asian and Pacific Rim attorneys general, and the insights gained and contacts made during international trips were "of considerable value in establishing and implementing DOJ's international agenda" (Evidence, p. 257).
  "Beginning in late 1989, [Thornburgh] became active in efforts to promote the rule of law in other nations. One extraordinary opportunity in this regard arose in the Soviet Union, which was in the throes of transformation. Premier Mikhail S. Gorbachev had undertaken to depart from the totalitarian past through glasnost (openness) and perestroika (restructuring). To help him create a 'law-based state,' the Soviet Ministry of Justice [and Justice Minister Veniamin F. Yakovlev] invited us to visit Moscow to discuss democracy, the rule of law and human rights ... marking the first visit ever by a sitting attorney general of the United States to the Soviet Union" (Evidence, p. 257). The Cold War was soon to end and of all those Thornburgh had met Yakovlev was the principal survivor. It is with him that a cordial relationship has extended into Thornburgh's ongoing career, with meetings both in Russia and in the United States, jointly promoting the rule of law.
  After years of commitment by both Dick and Ginny Thornburgh to extending the rights and opportunities of persons with disabilities, Attorney General Thornburgh was presented with a truly unique opportunity in the work to enact the landmark Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA). Thornburgh was proud to serve as the Bush administration's "point man" for this effort and the ADA was signed into law on July 26, 1990. Thornburgh states: "The day was a high point of my tenure as attorney general, and I will never forget the celebration of what columnist David Broder called 'arguably the most significant civil rights and social policy legislation to become law in more than a decade'." In signing the bill, President Bush presented signing pens to all on the stage, "but Harold Wilkie told him to give his pen (which he had accepted with his right foot) to Ginny Thornburgh in token of her vigorous efforts in support of the bill" (Evidence, p. 262). Both Dick and Ginny Thornburgh continue to be repeatedly recognized and celebrated for their commitment to persons with disabilities on into their ongoing careers, represented in this collection.
  Other matters on the domestic front that are also well represented in these files include Thornburgh's participation in the Council on Competitiveness (CC), the Domestic Policy Council (DPC), Economic Policy Council (EPC), judicial appointment issues, and the so-called Thornburgh Memorandum.
  On April 4, 1991, the news came of Pennsylvania Senator John Heinz's tragic death in a plane crash. A special election was to be held in the fall, to fill the vacancy. Governor Casey appointed his Labor and Industry Secretary, Harris Wofford, to serve in the interim. The Republicans, keen to hold onto the seat, encouraged Thornburgh to run for the office. And so it was that on June 4 Thornburgh told President Bush and his cabinet that he intended to resign and seek the Republican nomination for the position. Meanwhile a "bombshell" descended, in the form of a legal challenge by Jack Trinsey, regarding the procedures for filling the vacancy. Therefore, it was not until August 6 that the case was resolved and the election in November was a certainty. Thornburgh left office, precisely three years after he began as Attorney General, less than three months from election day.
  When addressing the assembled attorneys and staff for the last time as Attorney General of the United States, on August 15, 1991, Thornburgh proudly set forth their record of accomplishments and "I noted what a privilege it had been to spend a substantial part of my professional career, under five presidents, in the Department of Justice and called for God's blessing upon the Department, the men and women who make it work and all in this world who strive to achieve that which is good, right and just. With that I said, I was off to a 'first-ever Thornburgh family reunion [and] to my beloved Pennsylvania and an exciting campaign for the U.S. Senate.' I could not have imagined a more satisfying farewell from my colleagues" (Evidence draft, p. 839-40).
  The files here are in fourteen sections, as follow: Speeches; News Releases; Transcripts; Nomination and Confirmation; Attorney General's Files; Daily Schedules; Events; Foreign Trips; DPC, EPC, and CC; Department of Justice Issues; Weekly Reports; Correspondence; News Clippings; and Reports. Each section has an instructive and informative note to assist researchers.
  - Speeches and Testimony, 1.
    All 195 speeches delivered by Attorney General Thornburgh have been digitized and are available here online. These speeches cover virtually every major topic encountered during Thornburgh's three years at the Department of Justice, 1988-1991. The detail and issue background included makes them a very valuable source for researchers. In many cases, the collection also contains drafts and interesting "as delivered" copies.
    - Remarks of Dick Thornburgh Attorney General of the United States Following His Taking the Oath of Office, Washington, DC, August 12, 1988 (Box 739, Folder 1)
    - "Federalism and Law Enforcement," Second Annual Lawyers' Convention of the Federalist Society for Law and Public Policy Studies, Washington, DC, September 9, 1988 (Box 739, Folder 2)
    - "Reinvigorating Government," Carnegie Mellon University School of Urban and Public Affairs (SUPA), Pittsburgh, PA, September 29, 1988 (Box 739, Folder 3)
    - Philadelphia Bar Association, Washington, DC, September 30, 1988 (Box 739, Folder 4)
    - Department of Justice Employees, Washington, DC, October 7, 1988 (Box 739, Folder 5)
    - United States Attorneys' Conference, Charleston, SC, October 8, 1988 (Box 739, Folder 6)
    - International Association of Chiefs of Police Conference, Portland, OR, October 17, 1988 (Box 739, Folder 7)
    - Appeal of Conscience Foundation, New York, NY, October 18, 1988 (Box 739, Folder 8)
    - Dedication Ceremony of Franklin and Marshall College's Stager Hall, Lancaster, PA, October 20, 1988 (Box 739, Folder 9)
    - Organized Crime Drug Enforcement Task Forces Conference, San Diego, CA, October 25, 1988 (Box 739, Folder 10)
    - University of Florida Blue Key Banquet, Gainesville, FL, October 28, 1988 (Box 739, Folder 11)
    - Oceans '88 Conference, Baltimore, MD, October 31, 1988 (Box 739, Folder 12)
    - Allegheny Conference on Community Development, Pittsburgh, PA, November 14, 1988 (Box 739, Folder 13)
    - New England Council's 63rd Annual Dinner Meeting, Boston, MA, November 16, 1988 (Box 739, Folder 14)
    - Annual Dinner of the Pennsylvania Society, New York, NY, December 10, 1988 (Box 739, Folder 15)
    - Inauguration Sabbath Services the Washington Hebrew Congregation, Washington, DC, January 13, 1989 (Box 739, Folder 16)
    - 20th Annual Ecumenical Service Commemorating Dr. Martin Luther King, Atlanta, GA, January 16, 1989 (Box 739, Folder 17)
    - West Virginia Bar Association's Mid-Winter Meeting, Charleston, WV, February 3, 1989 (Box 739, Folder 18)
    - Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, concerning Fraud in the Savings and Loan Association Area, Washington, DC, February 9, 1989 (Box 739, Folder 19)
    - Council on Foreign Relations, Washington, DC, February 16, 1989 (Box 739, Folder 20)
    - Society of the Four Arts, Palm Beach, FL, February 21, 1989 (Box 739, Folder 21)
    - Economic Club of New York, NY, New York, February 22, 1989 (Box 739, Folder 22)
    - Washington Institute of the National Council of Jewish Women, Washington, DC, March 13, 1989 (Box 739, Folder 23)
    - Anti-Defamation League of B'Nai B'rith, Washington, DC, March 14, 1989 (Box 739, Folder 24)
    - Annual Meeting of Special Agents in Charge, Federal Bureau of Investigation and Drug Enforcement Administration, Phoenix, AZ, March 20, 1989 (Box 740, Folder 1)
    - "Three Mile Island," National Press Club, Washington, DC, March 28, 1989 (Box 740, Folder 2)
    - Pittsburgh World Affairs Council, Pittsburgh, PA, April 11, 1989 (Box 740, Folder 3)
    - Foundation for Developmental Disabilities, San Diego, CA, April 20, 1989 (Box 740, Folder 4)
    - Los Angeles World Affairs Council, Los Angeles, CA, April 24, 1989 (Box 740, Folder 5)
    - Seventh International Drug Enforcement Conference, Miami, FL, April 26, 1989 (Box 740, Folder 6)
    - House Judiciary Committee concerning Department of Justice Appropriation Authorization, Washington, DC, May 2, 1989 (Box 740, Folder 7)
    - Fifth and Eleventh Judicial Circuits, New Orleans, LA, May 8, 1989 (Box 740, Folder 8)
    - 1989 Graduating Class of the University of NC School of Law, Chapel Hill, NC, May 14, 1989 (Box 740, Folder 9)
    - American Law Institute, Washington, DC, May 19, 1989 (Box 740, Folder 10)
    - 1989 National Law Center, The George Washington University, Washington, DC, May 21, 1989 (Box 740, Folder 11)
    - Committee on the Judiciary United States Senate, concerning the Role of the American Bar Association in the Judicial Selection Process, Washington, DC, June 2, 1989 (Box 740, Folder 12)
    - TX Police Association, Fort Worth, TX, June 13, 1989 (Box 740, Folder 13)
    - Houston Lawyers Association Dinner, Houston, TX, June 13, 1989 (Box 740, Folder 14)
    - Caucus on International Narcotics Control, United States Senate, concerning United States International Drug Control Policy, New York, NY, June 19, 1989 (Box 740, Folder 15)
    - Senate Committee on Labor and Human Resources, concerning the Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA), Washington, DC, June 22, 1989 (Box 740, Folder 16)
    - Operation Push Annual Conference, Chicago, IL, June 27, 1989 (Box 740, Folder 17)
    - Program on Ethics and Management in Government Sponsored by the American Bar Association, Washington, DC, June 29, 1989 (Box 740, Folder 18)
    - American Legion, Pittsburgh, PA, July 12, 1989 (Box 740, Folder 19)
    - National Association of District Attorneys, Portland, ME, July 19, 1989 (Box 741, Folder 1)
    - Committee on Foreign Relations, United States Senate, concerning the United Nations Convention Against Illicit Traffic in Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances, Washington, DC, August 2, 1989 (Box 741, Folder 2)
    - "Back to Fundamentals - Meeting Expectations for Law Enforcement and the Administration of Justice," House of Delegates of the American Bar Association, Honolulu, Hawaii, August 8, 1989 (Box 741, Folder 3)
    - American Correctional Association, Baltimore, MD, August 14, 1989 (Box 741, Folder 4)
    - Senate Committee on the Judiciary and Committee on Governmental Affairs concerning Organized Crime Strike Forces, Washington, DC, September 8, 1989 (Box 741, Folder 5)
    - Department of Justice Securities Enforcement Conference, Washington, DC, September 12, 1989 (Box 741, Folder 6)
    - Third Circuit Judicial Conference, Pittsburgh, PA, September 12, 1989 (Box 741, Folder 7)
    - House Appropriations Subcommittee on the Departments of Commerce, Justice and State, the Judiciary, and Related Agencies, Washington, DC, September 13, 1989 (Box 741, Folder 8)
    - Presidential Forum on Offenders with Mental Retardation, Bethesda, MD, September 15, 1989 (Box 741, Folder 9)
    - Judicial Conference of the U.S., Washington, DC, September 20, 1989 (Box 741, Folder 10)
    - Sixth Annual General Counsel Briefing, Washington, DC, September 20, 1989 (Box 741, Folder 11)
    - Hispanic Heritage Month Celebration, Washington, DC, September 20, 1989 (Box 741, Folder 12)
    - Ceremonies Commemorating the Bicentennial of the Office of the United States Attorney General, Washington, DC, September 22, 1989 (Box 741, Folder 13)
    - Drug Free Business Initiative, San Antonio, TX, September 27, 1989 (Box 741, Folder 14)
    - U.S. Attorneys Conference, San Antonio, TX, September 27, 1989 (Box 741, Folder 15)
    - House Judiciary Committee on the Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA), Washington, DC, October 12, 1989 (Box 741, Folder 16)
    - "Glasnost, Perestroika, Democratizatsia and the Rule of Law," Moscow State University, Moscow, USSR, October 18, 1989 (Box 741, Folder 17)
    - American Bankers Association, New York, NY, October 26, 1989 (Box 741, Folder 18)
    - National Conference of the Religious Alliance Against Pornography, Washington, DC, October 26, 1989 (Box 742, Folder 1)
    - International Symposium on Money Laundering, Miami, FL, October 27, 1989 (Box 742, Folder 2)
    - Special Agent Memorial Services, Washington, DC, November 1, 1989 (Box 742, Folder 3)
    - Civil Rights Committee of the Anti-defamation League of B'Nai B'Rith, Philadelphia, PA, November 2, 1989 (Box 742, Folder 4)
    - National Association of Women Judges, Washington, DC, November 10, 1989 (Box 742, Folder 5)
    - Council of Jewish Federations, Inc., Cincinnati, OH, November 18, 1989 (Box 742, Folder 6)
    - National Crime Prevention Awards, Washington, DC, December 7, 1989 (Box 742, Folder 7)
    - "The Rule of Law: How Democracy Happens," British-American Parliamentary Group House of Commons, London, England, December 13, 1989 (Box 742, Folder 8)
    - Department of Justice Honoring Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr., Washington, DC, January 8, 1990 (Box 742, Folder 9)
    - Office of Personnel Management's Government-wide Conference on the Employment of Persons with Disabilities, Bethesda, MD, January 10, 1990 (Box 742, Folder 10)
    - Department of Justice Honoring Eagle Award Recipients, Washington, DC, January 10, 1990 (Box 742, Folder 11)
    - "The Separation of Powers: an Exemplar of the Rule of Law," The Federalist Society, Washington, DC, January 19, 1990 (Box 742, Folder 12)
    - "Codification and the Rule of Law," Conference on Criminal Code Reform; a Conference of the Society for the Reform of the Criminal Law, Washington, DC, January 22, 1990 (Box 742, Folder 13)
    - 38th Annual Attorney General's Awards Ceremony, Washington, DC, January 26, 1990 (Box 742, Folder 14)
    - Federal Courts Study Committee, Washington, DC, January 31, 1990 (Box 742, Folder 15)
    - Governor's Conference on Alcohol and Other Drugs, Des Moines, IA, February 8, 1990 (Box 742, Folder 16)
    - Linn County Bar Association Luncheon, Cedar Rapids, IA, February 8, 1990 (Box 742, Folder 17)
    - "The Rule of Law in Russia: How Democracy Might Work," Council on Foreign Affairs, New York, NY, February 13, 1990 (Box 742, Folder 18)
    - Ceremony Commemorating the Centennial of the Appointment of William Howard Taft as Solicitor General, Washington, DC, February 22, 1990 (Box 742, Folder 19)
    - Simon Wiesenthal Center's First Annual Leadership Conference Breakfast, Washington, DC, March 6, 1990 (Box 742, Folder 20)
    - Nashville Exchange Club Luncheon, Nashville, TN, March 9, 1990 (Box 742, Folder 21)
    - 1990 Neighborhood Watch Awards Breakfast, Memphis, TN, March 10, 1990 (Box 742, Folder 22)
    - University of TN Centennial Law Review Banquet, Knoxville, TN, March 10, 1990 (Box 743, Folder 1)
    - Judicial Conference of the United States, Washington, DC, March 13, 1990 (Box 743, Folder 2)
    - Seattle Rotary Club, Seattle, Washington, March 21, 1990 (Box 743, Folder 3)
    - University of Puget Sound Law School, Seattle, Washington, March 21, 1990 (Box 743, Folder 4)
    - Greater Spokane Substance Abuse Council Luncheon, Spokane, Washington, March 22, 1990 (Box 743, Folder 5)